<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A court of guard for the heart.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5876.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633130</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2111:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A court of guard for the heart.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug: Mathewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Ioseph Taylor.</note>
                  <note>Headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸, F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, stained, and with print show-through, and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs IV, 23 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173946:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173946:1"/>
            <p>A COVRT OF GVARD FOR THE HEART.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Aug: Mathewes</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173946:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173946:2"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE AND FERVENT Louer of Religion, Sir GEORGE HASTINGS, <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EEting with this <hi>Copy</hi> by accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; per uſing it with obſeruation and delight,
<pb facs="tcp:173946:3"/>J found it too worthy to be buried in obſcuritie, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fined to one priuate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And though the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Author, (who is to me, after much inquiry, ſtill vnknowne) for what cauſe I cannot gueſſe, did omit to bleſſe the World with ſo happy a fruit of his Labours; J preſumed to bring it foorth to that light, which otherwiſe it was likely neuer to haue ſeene. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the hope to make that, which was at
<pb facs="tcp:173946:3"/>firſt good, ſo much the better, by being more publicke and generall Not that it ſhall lye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſale on euery Booke-ſellers ſtall, but onely bee commended into the hands of ſome fewe noble and worthy <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> Among whom, I am principally encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your Zealous affection to ſuch holy Pieces, and Diuine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, to Dedicate it
<pb facs="tcp:173946:4"/>and my ſelfe to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of your VVorſhip not doubting of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious reſpect to ſo graue a Gueſt, and free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips vnworthy Seruant <hi>IOSEPH TAYLOR.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173946:4"/>
            <head>A COVRT OF <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARD.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Keepe thy Heart with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, for out of it come iſſues of Life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>One ſpeakes more feelingly of a ſtorm, then hee that hath ſuffered Shipwracke; none, of the loſſe of innocence, more punctually, then the broken, the decayed, the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerupt ſinner: for as ſome
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173946:5"/>men that haue vndone them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by ſuites of Law, haue yet got the knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be good Lawyers; or as other by their many diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes haue out of their Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries bills, made vp a booke of Medicines: ſo doth the deare experiment of our ſins prooue vs good Counſellors for others, (though by a ſtrange argument) becauſe we haue bene ill ones to our ſelues. There was a time when none kept his heart with leſſe diligence then <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> did, when if his wiues had bin made out of his ſide, as <hi>Eue</hi> was out of <hi>Adams,</hi> he had bene a monſter of ſeuen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173946:5"/>hundred ribbs at leaſt;<note place="margin">1. King. 11.3.</note> for ſo many wiues hee had beſides his Concubines. There was a time when euery wanton eye had a flame for him to ſinge himſelfe by, euery tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation had a picklocke to his breſt to enter in at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; when his heart was like a ſhiuered glaſſe, reflecting ſo many ſeuerall ſinnes as there was pieces of it; his Cinque ports of ſenſes, vnder an ill guardian, ſo many inlets for treaſon; himſelfe a Captiue, though a King, a ſlaue in ſin, though a Royal one: So that <hi>Tertullian</hi> durſt ſay, <hi>Solomon quite loſt that glory which God gaue him.</hi> And Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:173946:6"/>with as much ſharpenes, but mingling with it a wiſh of pitty, ſayth of him, <hi>Hee built God a Temple, but I could wiſh, he had not let the Temple of his heart to fall to ruine.</hi> There were not more workmen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the building of the one, then there were foule ſinnes buſie in deſtroying of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: his heart went downe farre faſter then the Temple roſe, as if God had meant ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiuely in one patterne to haue drawne to the life, the beſt of his graces, the worſt of our ſins; ſhewing <hi>Solomon</hi> to the world, like the ſame picture with two reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; look on him on that ſide
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173946:6"/>where God portrayed him, with his Intellectuals ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med aboue his fellowes, you ſhall find an Angel: ſtep on the other ſide, wher he drew himſelfe in his own colours of Idolatry, you ſhall ſee a deuill; For a ſinner is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe hauing had that name (the only title of his, which the Pope leaues out) <hi>get thee behinde me Satan.</hi> Let this therefore bee the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of the Speaker, that he that knew what the loſſe of a heart was, giues you counſell cheape, which hee dearely bought. <hi>Keepe thy heart with all diligence for out of it come iſſues of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173946:7"/>
            <p>But I muſt not doe <hi>Solomon</hi> that wrong as to gaze on him in his falling, not to caſt a glance on him in his riſing; beſide, it may be my Text may ſuffer in it; the counſaile may bee leſſe welcome if it be thought a condemned Sinner gaue it: Yet we ſhall find,<note place="margin">1 King. 17.6.</note> 
               <hi>Elias</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not his meate, becauſe a Rauen (an vncleane Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) broght it to him:<note place="margin">Gal, 1, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Should an Angell preach any other Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell then this</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>let him be accurſed;</hi> But, he ſayth not, ſhould the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil preach no other then this, Let this Goſpel bee accurſt? Had <hi>Solomon</hi> at that time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173946:7"/>when he bended his knees to the Idoll <hi>Aſteroth</hi> (which by many of the Learned is thought to haue bin the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Venus,</hi> a fit Goddes for his turne) had he then, I ſay, pronounced, that the true God were onely to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhould wee retyre our Faith from it becauſe an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later ſpoke it? But to what ende is it that <hi>Solomons</hi> ſinnes are ſhewen in ſuch a Scarlet, as if the whole ſea of Chriſts Paſsion could not waſh it out? Why it needs be thought that hee is damned, whoſe words, no doubt, haue ſent more ſoules to heauen, then there are letters in them; who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173946:8"/>was an immediate Secretary to God, nay, a Royall type of Chriſt: he ſinned indeed, in that he was no type of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no more was <hi>Ionas</hi> in his fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away from God, or <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in being deceiued by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah:</hi> yet both types of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But it troubles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they find it regiſtred, hee ſinned; but they find it no were that he repented. But their Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie might teach them that in matters of fact, arguments of authoritie drawne from negatiues are but weake; it is not written that he repented, therefore hee did not repent, is but a looſe vngrounded conſequence: Where do they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173946:8"/>find that <hi>Adam</hi> repented of his ſin in Paradiſe, <hi>Noah</hi> of his Drunkenneſſe, or <hi>Lot</hi> of his Inceſt; are theſe therefore in the <hi>black-booke</hi> of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? But ſuppoſe it be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, what action ſhall <hi>Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> haue againſt them for ſo high an Iniury? I am ſure S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> whoſe credite may waigh down a whole Colledge of Cardinals, though weighty <hi>Bellarmin</hi> makes one againſt him, cites a place for it out of <hi>Solomons</hi> himſelfe, where the <hi>Septuagint</hi> tranſlate it out of the originall (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe rendred in our Engliſh) <hi>at laſt I repented.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24.32</note> If this moue not, yet let Gods promiſe be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173946:9"/>of ſome credit, which was made ſo firme for <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7, 15.</note> 
               <hi>I will be his Father, he ſhall be my Sonne: if he commit iuiquitie, I will chasten him with the rod of men, But my mercy ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part away from him as I tooke it from</hi> Saul, <hi>whom I put away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</hi> Marke the words, <hi>If he commit iniquity, he would cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten him,</hi> but how? <hi>with the rod of Men,</hi> But where in the Scripture, is <hi>the Rod of men</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for damnation? <hi>He would take his mercy from him;</hi> but how? <hi>not as hee did from Saul</hi> that was a Reprobate; why therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate?</p>
            <p>I confeſſe the Fathers are not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173946:9"/>very tender handed in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the faults of <hi>Solomon;</hi> but he that reades them, may ſoone finde the reaſon was becauſe the vulgar Iewes tooke <hi>Solomon</hi> to be Chriſt, for the noyſing of him to be the Meſsias was the cauſe (as ſome imagine) the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> tooke ſo long a ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to viſite him; Therefore S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> well coniectures. <hi>God it may be ſuffered him to ſin ſo fouly, least others ſhould (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with the rariety of his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) ſinne more fowly in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing him to be God;</hi> But ſhall we therefore infer God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffered him to be damned? I would not pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173946:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>greateſt ſinner that I ſhould ſee dye, though I ſhould viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly perceiue his ſins to couer him like a cloude, as if they would keepe God from loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on him, the deuill wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for him, as for a certaine prey, yet I would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it? <hi>The wayes of thy mercies O God, are paſt finding out, more vnknowne then the way of a Ship in the ſea, or of an Eagle in the ayre.</hi> Let them ſhew me how a flaſh of Lightening melts the Sword without making any impreſsion in the Scabberd: I will ſhew them as well, how at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of our death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy more ſuddaine, and more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173946:10"/>penetrating then the Lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, may melt our hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to repentance, though out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly the eyes of the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by perceiue it not. Of the two then, I dare ſay, the Pope offends the leſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more charitably in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizing them for Saints, who for ought hee knowes are damned, then theſe do in damning them, who for ought they know are Saints. But I will no longer tract the vncharitable footſteps of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> cenſurers; more I might ſay, to ſecure him from their malice, leſſe I could not. I will leaue them onely with this aduiſe, To beſtow more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173946:11"/>time in ſauing their owne ſoules; leſſe, in damning of the ſoules of others! For <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith not heere, Damne another mans heart with all diligence, but <hi>Keepe thy heart with all diligence, for out of it come iſſues of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt counſel that euer was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt able Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor that euer was; for we haue already diſcouered him to bee no leſſe then <hi>Solomon;</hi> one that leaueled the vneuen wayes of knowledge from the <hi>Caedar of Libanus to the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop that groweth on the wall;</hi> that had traced the Labyrinth of all ſecrets without a thred, and left neuer a knot in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173946:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to vnty; to whom God himſelfe had ſaid, <hi>There was none like thee before thee, nor ſhall any ariſe after thee that is like thee.</hi> Preferred therefore for his <hi>Wiſdome</hi> by <hi>Abulenſis,</hi> before <hi>Adam</hi> in his Originall perfection: nay (that which toucheth vs more nere) one that exactly knewe the true value of a heart, aſwell by the loſſe, as by the enioying. He it is giues you the aduice, as a ſhort exact drawne out of the large coppy of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, <hi>Keepe thy heart with all diligence:</hi> nor onely ſo, he preſcribs not as ignorant <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricks</hi> giue Phiſick, take this, but ask me not why; or as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173946:12"/>
               <hi>Tyrants</hi> giue Lawes, obey this, my will is my reaſon: For he hath a <hi>quia</hi> for you, as well as a <hi>quid,</hi> a why, aſwell as a what, <hi>For out of it come iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues of life.</hi> Thy <hi>Heart</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a Iewell, thy Body the Cabinet, the Guardian thy Selfe; the Watch, <hi>all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;</hi> the motiue of all, <hi>Life Keepe thy heart with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, for out of it come iſſues of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſuruey ſhal be of the <hi>Iewell,</hi> a Iewell of Gods own cutting; he that only La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary, if you marke the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of it; you may eaſily find it, large and open to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heauen, but angular
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173946:12"/>and narrow, and ſhut vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the earth. Aske the Philoſopher what the <hi>Heart</hi> is, he will tell you, <hi>It is the fountaine of life, the furnace of heate, and centre of the bloud:</hi> But aske the Diuine, and you ſhal heare, <hi>It is a Ray, a Spark an Image of the Diuinitie;</hi> It is the ſoule it ſelfe in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>With the heart man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeus vnto righteouſnes. Make the heart of this thy people fat</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſaiah</hi>) but why?<note place="margin">Eſay 6.10</note> 
               <hi>Leſt they vnderſtand with the heart.</hi> So that as St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, The Court hath gott the attribute of the Queene that dwells in it, the Queene the name of her Court, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173946:13"/>
               <hi>Heart,</hi> the attributes of the <hi>Soule;</hi> the <hi>Soule</hi> in exchange, the name, the title of the <hi>Heart.</hi> To keepe therefore thy <hi>Heart,</hi> is as much, as to keepe thy <hi>Soule,:</hi> Nay, Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> will tell you, <hi>That to keepe your Heart is as much as to keepe thy God.</hi> For doe but open thy ſeuerall Cloſet there, and there you ſhall find a neſt of Iewels invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and ſhut vp one within another. Open thy <hi>Heart,</hi> thou ſhalt find thy <hi>Soule</hi> there; open thy <hi>Soule,</hi> thou ſhalt meet thy <hi>Spirit</hi> there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnfold thy <hi>Spirit,</hi> thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee thy <hi>Faith;</hi> vnlocke thy <hi>Faith,</hi> and thy <hi>God</hi> will ſhew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173946:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelfe. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> therefore iuſtly cryeth out vnto vs, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne not O man, this miracle within thee, doe not vndervalue the heart which God hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richt.</hi> What madneſſe is it to think meanly of your <hi>Soules,</hi> which the Deuil eſteemes ſo precious. He wageth warre againſt God himſelfe, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, he watcheth, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the world to gaine one heart. If thou wilt not take ſome care to keep, what the deuill beſtowes ſo much to gaine, muſt it not follow that thou thinkeſt far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thy ſelfe then the deuill doth?</p>
            <p>If nothing elſe will teach
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173946:14"/>thee the value of they heart, know it is the onely glaſſe that God delights to look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in, it is a letter written by himſelfe to himſelfe, as wel directed to God, as ſent from him; the Inſcription his, the Superſcription his: It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sacrifice, his Altar, and his Temple, it is a Sterling piece of Gods owne Coine, a Medall on which he ſtampe his Image, and in that ſtampe thou mayſt read thy value.</p>
            <p>I haue ſaid enough, but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all, yet did euer any affirme the ſhadow to be worth the ſubſtance, or the Picture worth the face of him it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth. Yet St. <hi>Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:173946:14"/>hath a ſtrain aboue this, with ſo exact compleatneſſe was our Redemption accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, <hi>God laying downe at ſtake his ſoule, for the ſoule of man that was forfeited, as if the ſoule of a ſinner were worth the ſoule of his God.</hi> Bold words, holy Father, <hi>the ſoule of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner worth the life of his God:</hi> worth thoſe <hi>ſtripes,</hi> thoſe <hi>buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetings,</hi> thoſe <hi>riuers of bloud,</hi> that <hi>Paſsion,</hi> nay that <hi>Death?</hi> Had not the leaſt droppe, or the eaſieſt groane of Chriſt, beene ranſome enough for more worlds, then there were euer men from <hi>Adam</hi> to this houre. Had not the very act of deſcending from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173946:15"/>his Glory into the boſome of the Virgin merited as much. Yet ſuch was the will of our bleſſed Sauiour, that could it bee ſuppoſed there were but one loſt ſoule in al the world, imagine it were onely thine, yet he would haue come into the world, &amp; would haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all thoſe torments, to haue ſaued that one Soule of thine, for Chriſt dyed as much for one as for all; in the ſhare of his Paſsion as in the enioying of the Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine; All hath all, euery one hath all. I can goe no higher in the valuing of this Iewell; it ſhall be my wiſh that none here euer goe lower in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of it. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173946:15"/>of the minde, <hi>That if the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or the pooreſt man amongſt vs did but knowe how noble his heart were, what honours, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and priuiledges it had, hee would ſcorne as much to diſhonor it with ſinne, as a great Prince would doe to pilfer for his din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> For do but thinke with your ſelues, what haue your deare, your familiar ſinnes in them, worth a heart that <hi>God</hi> hath dyed for: before you part with it, looke vpon it; a Prodigall will do ſo much for his money, though hee throw it away afterward: ſee what you change, ſee for what, obſerue from whom you take it, to whom you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173946:16"/>giue it, remember what ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes it muſt ſuffer, if you part wath it. When you haue done this, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> lets you looſe, <hi>Sinne if thou canſt who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere thou art, for either thou art already an incarnate Deuill, or by this thou ſhalt ouercome the Deuill.</hi> Thus let me leaue this Iewell a while in truſt with your eares, till I haue found a Cabinet for it, which is my next <hi>Search, thy heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soules once ſeperated needs no looking too, but while they are here vnited, they are neither without their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor their Guardians: <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſe pillars of bones that wee ſee couered with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173946:16"/>fleſh, ſpread ouer with Nerues and vaines, the Face, the Breſt and Hands, make vp but one Fabricke of a Priſon, to keepe the vnruly Heart in: Priſon and Priſoner both at a time;</hi> For ſaith <hi>Tertullian, As ſoone as the priſon is made, the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is in.</hi> But <hi>Epictetus</hi> will not grant the body a name of ſo much ſtrength as a Priſon, with him it goes for no more then a <hi>China diſh, an artificiall durt,</hi> or <hi>Clay neatly made vp. Plautus</hi> the <hi>Comaedian</hi> hath an other ſtraine for it, he calles man the <hi>Saltſeller of his owne ſoule.</hi> But as it is a defence which women vſe, when it is vrged to them, why there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173946:17"/>ſhould be left in Story, more arguments of the malice of their Sex then of men: to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that, the reaſon is, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men are the writers of thoſe Stories, not women: So wee may vſe the like in theſe titles, of diſparagement of the body, That the Soule was the Inuentor of them, not the Body. But whether a <hi>Priſon,</hi> or a <hi>Chinadiſh,</hi> or a <hi>Saltſeller,</hi> or what elſe they pleaſe to call this outward frame of ours, it muſt needs be the only Casket of this Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well which we haue ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly priſed: nor ſhal we leſſe in a proportion eſteem the <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kee</hi> the the <hi>Iewel Teroul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Far be it that God ſhould for euer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173946:17"/>forſake that Body which was the Diuine work of his own hand, the Maſter-peece of his Art, the Viall of his breath, the Heyre of his bounty, the Prieſt of his religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>the Souldier of his teſtimony the Siſter of his Chriſt:</hi> If <hi>Tertullian</hi> weigh to lieghly Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Words in the Scales: <hi>Know ye not that yeare the Teple of God, that the Spirit of God dweleth in you? If any Man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy, for the Temple of God is ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, which Temple you are.</hi> It was ſcoffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> put vpon <hi>Galba,</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> of better wit then face, that <hi>Galbas</hi> neat wit had a foul dwelling; But the Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian needs not feare any ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173946:18"/>by-word, for Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayth, <hi>That the Fleſh of a Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is as fayre to God, as his that is bath'd in Milke and Spices;</hi> Nor can a good Soule euer complaine iuſtly of an ill lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for though the walles of this thy Houſe of Fleſh totter with a Palſay, though they flame about thee with a Feauer, or fall to ruine with old Age, though thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an entire Hoſpitall of all Diſeaſes within thy ſelfe, yet as long as thou haſt not parted with this Iewell of <hi>Solomons,</hi> if neyther thy eyes haue pauned it to Luſt, nor thy eares morgaged it to Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, nor thy will ſold it our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173946:18"/>right to preſumptuous &amp; to raigning Sinnes: If it be thine owne Heart in thine owne Body (for to alienate one, is to make away both, for let none thinke he can giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Body to his Sinnes, and keepe his Soule for his God) but if both be thine, be aſſured God will keepe both of them thine, &amp; will make vp the defects of both If both be not thine, powre out thy prayers, that it would pleaſe thy angry God to giue thee thy ſelfe againe, that Chriſts wounded heart may ſend thee back thy heart vnwou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with this, with this warning reuited through the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173946:19"/>midſt of it, <hi>Hereafter, keepe thy Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Soule is ſo inſinuated into the Body, with ſo nere ſo cloſe a combination, that it poſed <hi>Tertullian</hi> (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth) to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, <hi>Whether the Body Cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the Soule, or the Soule the Body.</hi> On the ſame hinges we may hang another doubt, which may be ſaid to keepe the other; For looke on the <hi>Soule</hi> diſcuſsing, deciding, &amp; commanding all, you will ſay, ſhee is the Guardian: Looke again on the <hi>Body,</hi> ſee in it the ſeuerall ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the <hi>Senſes;</hi> the <hi>Eyes</hi> watching, the <hi>Eares</hi> liſtning, all ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173946:19"/>Sentinels, &amp; the whole frame of it like a well built Caſtle, it might tempt you to beleeue, that the Body had the charge giuen of keeping the <hi>Heart.</hi> But ſince the Guard may as well be ſaid to keepe the King, as the King the Guard, we will leaue the care between them, wiſhing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that neither of them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as <hi>Kain,</hi> did,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper.</hi> For the Heart wil one day giue account for the luſtfull wandring of the Eye, the Eye ſhall giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for betraying of the Heart. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſame fire ſhall then hold them, that no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally in the ſame flame;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173946:20"/>collegue fellowes they haue bene in ſinne, and God will not part them in the puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt reſolution then of theſe words wilbe, <hi>Heart keepe thy ſelfe.</hi> But it is a high way ſaying, <hi>That he that learns of none but himſelfe, hath a foole to his teacher.</hi> How then ſhall the <hi>heart</hi> that is kept by none but it ſelfe, haue no wiſet a Guardian? I feare no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. <hi>Dauid</hi> hath therefore found out another for the cuſtody; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vnleſſe God keepes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2</note> 
               <hi>the watchman wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but in vaine.</hi> Hee that keepes the <hi>Spheres</hi> in their motions, the <hi>Sunne</hi> with a whole army of Ieſſer lights
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173946:20"/>in their courſes, he that ſets the Sea his bounds, <hi>Thus far ſhalt thou paſſe, but no farther;</hi> He that hanges the whole World vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hindges, is as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thee as of the whole world; nor doth he leaue thee only to his generall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, as <hi>Pelagius</hi> (too proud of the ſtrength of his owne Heart) would haue it; He doth not winde thee vp as a Watch, then giue thee vp to thine owne motion, but ſayth Saint <hi>Auſtine, When he hath ſent his Graces as Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bengers to prepare thy heart, he continues them there to guard thy Heart:</hi> Doe but recount to your ſelues the Stories of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173946:21"/>your own liues. Remember how often your hearts haue bene reſolutely ſet on ſuch, or ſuch a ſinn, yet God hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted them: How often haue your tongues bene rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to blaſpheme, or ſlander, yet <hi>God</hi> hath ſtopd them; and your hands prepared for a miſchiefe, yet <hi>God</hi> hath ſtayd them. How this affects you I know not, but St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was ſo taken with it, when he thought on't, that it made him ſpeake thoſe words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which nothing but ſuch a zeale, ſuch a deuotion, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had, could make warrantable? <hi>Such are the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to my ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:173946:21"/>that I can ſcarſe imagine God doth any thing els, but ſtudy how to ſaue me; as if hee had forgot all the reſt of his creatures, to haue the more time to looke to me alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this all; but as great <hi>Princes</hi> will haue their Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uants attend on him whom they honor: ſo <hi>God</hi> comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds the glorious Angels to wait on their Harts, on whom he caſts a gratious eye, nay, <hi>They are no longer Angels,</hi> (as St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> well obſerues) <hi>then they are ſo employd:</hi> For according to S. <hi>Auſtin, An Angel is a name of Office, not of Nature.</hi> They are alwayes <hi>Spirits,</hi> but not alwayes <hi>Angels,</hi> for no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173946:22"/>meſſengers from <hi>God</hi> to man, no longer <hi>Angels;</hi> ſince onely to be a Meſſenger, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to be an <hi>Angell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That euery one of vs hath a ſeuerall <hi>Angell</hi> deputed for his guard from his natiuitie, is the iudgement of ſome of the learned Fathers: Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> proues the dignity of the ſoule by that argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>St. Baſil</hi> as confidently ſayes <hi>That euery true beleeuer hath his Angell:</hi> the like ſayes <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> of euery one that is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. Others of later times, haue gone ſo far, as to affirm, our Sauiour Chriſt while he liued on earth, had his tutela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Angell: becauſe it is ſayd that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173946:22"/>
               <hi>when he was in that bloudyagony in the Garden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.</note> 
               <hi>there appeared an Angell from heauen comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him.</hi> But the bold fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the <hi>Ieſuite Maldonat,</hi> bluſheth at this, reiecting it for a Paradoxe, <hi>That hee that was the true God ſhould want the guard of one ſingle Angell. Bellarmins</hi> Meditations haue eleuated him to ſo high a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as to find out, that in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Kingdome there are two Kings, a Man and an Angel; in euer Dioces two Biſhops, a Man and an Angel; nay, in the Catholike Church two Popes without a Schiſme, the one a viſible Man, the other an inuiſible Angell. But wee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173946:23"/>knowledge is bounded o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the one ſide with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, on the other ſide, by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne modeſty, do willingly forbeare to giue you dreames inſtead of Reuelations, Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, inſtead of Truth. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euery Soule of vs hath a ſeuerall Angell for a Tutor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Let it reſt with thoſe Fathers that thought ſo: But whether each of vs hath a bad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to oppoſe, as a good to aſsiſt, as <hi>Maldonat</hi> thinks pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable? or whether at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, euery mans good Angell ſhall gather together the bones of him he guarded, as <hi>Suarez</hi> teacheth: Or as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will haue it, <hi>In the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173946:23"/>Chaire of Rome there bee ſeated an inuiſible Pope, as well as a viſible;</hi> Let the Ieſuits only determine, that haue made themſelues a falſe Key to the Cabinet of <hi>Gods</hi> ſecrets. It ſhall ſuffice vs to whom the Fooliſhneſſe of the reuealed <hi>Goſpell</hi> is ſufficient, <hi>That hee that maks his Angels miniſtring spirits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; his Miniſters a flame of Fire, hath giuen his Angles charge ouer vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſai 91.11</note> 
               <hi>to keepe vs in all our wayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daniel 10</note> In <hi>Daniel</hi> wee find but one Angell to guard a whole Kingdome, all <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 32.</note> In <hi>Geneſis</hi> two Armies of Angels to keepe one <hi>Iacob.</hi> Of their protection wee are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, of their number whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173946:24"/>one or more, wee may be with religion euough vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes vs neereſt, is to make ſuch vſe of it, which St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> doth on thoſe words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready cited; <hi>He gaue his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels charge ouer thee.</hi> O what reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhould theſe words ſtrike in thee, what deuotion ſhould they ſtirre vp, what confidence to heare that thy Angels are thy guides, to hear that they are not onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thee, but preſent for thee: they are the coniuring words of that deuout Father, <hi>Let mee beſeech you Brethren, that yee would not commit thoſe foule ſinnes in the ſight of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173946:24"/>Angels that keepe you in the eyes of God himſelf, which you would not doe if no more then I were by? If you will needs ſin</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Baſil</hi>) <hi>chuſe out ſome place where neither God nor his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are; but if their be no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo darke, ſo ſolitary, ſo ſecret, but they are there, let there as well be no place for you to dare to ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue ſhowne you the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of the Angels vnder God the great Keeper of all harts; That there is a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly watch dayly ſet about vs. I will onely adde this out of St. <hi>Baſil, That God, nor his Angels neuer part with vs, till
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173946:25"/>we make them goe, that only our ſins diſmiſſe this Watch. For as ſmoake driues away Bees</hi> (ſaith that Father) <hi>or as ill ſmels chaſe Pigeons from their Doue-coats, ſo doth the ſmoake, the ſtench of ſinne driue God from vs with all his Angels.</hi> Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vnregenerate Sinner complaine that his <hi>Heart</hi> is not in Gods keeping: For had he not throwne durt on it himſelfe, nay, had hee not razed out of it the Image of the <hi>Deitie,</hi> as a Thiefe doth the marke of ſtollen Plate, that the owner ſhould not know it, <hi>God</hi> had ſtill kept it. But he keepes no defaced <hi>Hearts,</hi> nor yet no counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173946:25"/>he keepes no careleſſe, vnregarded, throwne-away hearts. <hi>Heart</hi> keepe thy ſelfe, muſt be the watchword; that paſsion that meetes thee without that word, let it not liue a minute longer; for there is no greater Treaſon then ſelfe-Treaſon, when the betrayer, and the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpell but one man.</p>
            <p>But it troubled St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> much, how the <hi>heart</hi> ſhould keepe the <hi>heart,</hi> when the <hi>heart</hi> would ſo ſeldome obey the <hi>heart.</hi> It makes him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with admiration; <hi>The minde commands the body, it is obeyd; the minde commands it ſelfe, it is reſiſted; bid thy feet
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173946:26"/>ſtirre, or thy hands moue, or thy eyes turn, in a moment it is done, with ſuch eaſe and ſuddenneſſe, that you can ſcarſe diſtinguiſh the performance from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: but the Heart commands the Heart, to will this, or that good; which it had not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded had it not willed, yet doth it not will what is commanded.</hi> He ends with the admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he began, <hi>What Prodegie is this, what Oedipus ſhall vnrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it?</hi> But the good Father findes it out at laſt, <hi>For</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the Heart turnes but halfe a fide on good actions, it lookes on them but with one eye; if it chance to bid farewell to ſinne, it is as fooliſh friends part, with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173946:26"/>many lookings backe, many excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſtil one farewel more.</hi> When Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> himſelfe in his yonger dayes, prayed to God for <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi> he confeſſeth he could not keep his rebellious <hi>heart</hi> from adding, <hi>giue mee chaſtitie, but not yet O God, let me haue ſome pleaſure more.</hi> No wonder then if the heart bee not obeyed, that would not be obeyed: if ſin depart not, when the heart will not let it goe. To cloſe vp this, if we baniſh ſinne, it muſt bee withall the heart; if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine God, it muſt be into all the heart. If we keep our <hi>hearts</hi> it muſt be withall dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: So ſhall we bee able
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173946:27"/>to beare a part in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſong, <hi>My heart is ready, O God, my heart is ready, for I haue kept my heart with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue wee ſeene the Iewell that is guarded, the watch ſet, the watchword giuen; we are now to walk the round to ſee the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: For St. <hi>Bernard</hi> will haue <hi>Solomon</hi> heere meane a Military watch, that is, <hi>keep thy heart through al the watches of the night:</hi> So that we all lye perdue vnder Martiall law, <hi>he that ſleepes dyes for it.</hi> The Originall word <hi>Samarah</hi> (as it is obſerued by <hi>Scalager</hi>) will well beare it: for it not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173946:27"/>onely ſignifieth the place, the ſtation of the watch: as it is ſaid in <hi>Baruch, the Stars ſhined in their watches.</hi> But the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Watch it ſelfe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.6</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule wayteth for the Lord, more then they that watch vnto the morning, I ſay, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that watch vnto the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning.</hi> The Antients diuided the night into foure Watches; two from the Euening to the firſt crowing of the Cocke; two from the crowing of the Cocke to the riſing of the morning. Theſe night wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Origen</hi> ſeconded by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> compared to the foure ages of man, <hi>his Infancy, his Youth, his Manhood,</hi> &amp; <hi>his Olde
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173946:28"/>Age:</hi> So that you may now perceiue what it is to keepe your hearts all the Watches of the night; it is no leſſe then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy Cradle to thy death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; from the firſt moment that God kindled a light of knowledge in thy heart, till the laſt when hee ſhall put it out: a light indeed ſo dimne, that the Fathers doubted not to compare it to the night; yet by that light, by that weake light, that glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, we are all to watch; Nor did our Sauiour bluſh to be likened to a Thiefe that ſhould come in ſuch a night; for he that tooke on him our Nature, ſhames not at the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173946:28"/>name of our vices; ſo that he by that name may keepe vs waking? But whether he come as a Thief, or as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe in the ſecond or third watches,<note place="margin">Luke 12.38.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed are the ſeruants whom he finds thus watching.</hi> But why in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third onely, St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> makes queſtion of? why names hee neither the firſt watch nor the laſt? Hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, the firſt is implied in the ſecond, but the laſt is left out as deſperate. Hee that dreames out the firſt watch, may awake in the ſecond, he that ſhuts his eyes in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, may open them in the third: But hee that drinkes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173946:29"/>downe ſinne like <hi>Opium</hi> to ſleepe with it, till the conuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of old age, or the laſt crampe of death awake him,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.</note> ſhall be like wretched <hi>Nabal</hi> who when hee had ſlept, found that his hart was dead within him. But let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you brethren to awake before that howre awakes you; to remember how fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a thing it is to fal into the hands of an angry God, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yee haue ſo often mocked with delayes, as you meant to coſen your ſelues to hell in ſpight of heauen. Yet make a ſtand, looke backe on the time, which you haue rather throwne away then ſpent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:173946:29"/>flatter not your ſelues, that the laſt Watch is farre from you, for none is truely young that is olde enough to dye: To ſhut vp all, vſe but that wit, that ſtudy, that diligence to ſaue your ſoules, which you haue done to damne them. For God requires no more of you, then his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; you haue ſpared neither time, nor coſt, nor trouble in the Deuils ſeruice, <hi>You haue loſt your harts with al diligence;</hi> In Gods ſeruice doe but ſo much, <hi>Keepe your hearts with all diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither <hi>Loue,</hi> a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or the <hi>Deitie</hi> endures a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, neither a deuided <hi>diligence</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:173946:30"/>or a deuided <hi>heart</hi> can ſerue Gods turne. Though the <hi>Tranſlators</hi> therefore differ, whether it be <hi>Cuſtodia, Cura,</hi> or <hi>Munitio,</hi> whether <hi>ex</hi> or <hi>prae</hi> be affixed, yet in the intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in the word of latitude, they all agree; For, whether we looke vpon the <hi>watch</hi> we ſet about our <hi>hearts,</hi> it muſt be no ſlumbring, no ſupine, nor intermitted watch; or on the care with which wee <hi>watch,</hi> it muſt bee no looſe, ſcattered, diſtracted, or agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh care that comes by fits; or on the places, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we watch the Forts or Block houſes, the inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes, all muſt bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173946:30"/>man'd. Since therefore ſinne aſſayles euery where, wee muſt be armed euery where. If we do but obſerue nature, we ſhall finde by her placing of the <hi>Heart,</hi> how we ſhould <hi>keepe</hi> it: Firſt, it is ſeated with all aduantage of intelligence, almoſt in the center of man, with a curious net of veines, ſpred from it ouer all the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; like the Spider in the midſt of her web, which fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the leaſt touch that ſhakes her worke, retires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly from the danger: So ſhould the Soule ſhrinke at the leaſt noyſe, whiſpering, or murmure of ſin, it ſhould auoyd the very complement,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173946:31"/>the firſt addreſſe of it, and to be ſenſible of danger at the very ſight, the glimpſe of a Temptation. But this is not all that <hi>Nature</hi> hath bleſt the <hi>Heart</hi> with; for beſides this ſcituation of aduantage, it hath a double natural fence, the one more inward, a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, though firme skinne, to enwrap the <hi>heart</hi> with; the other, an outward ſtrong wall of ribbs. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> in his booke of <hi>Adoration,</hi> bids vs note it as remarkable, <hi>That the firſt ruine of this wall was in Paradiſe, when God tooke a ribb out of Adam to make a woman of: ſo that the forming of our firſt Mother, hath cauſed many of her
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173946:31"/>Sonns the looſing of their hearts;</hi> For as St. <hi>Cyril</hi> followes the <hi>Allegory: Euer ſince that time, ſinne aſſayles the heart at that place where it wants that rib for to defend it.</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralizeth the <hi>Ribbs</hi> into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my rational Vertues encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing the heart like the ſtrong men about the bed of <hi>Solomon,</hi> The <hi>tender skinne of the heart</hi> he makes to bee the <hi>tender Conſcience, For hee that wraps not vp his heart in a ſoft, a cleane, and vnſeared Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is either about to make a forfeit of it, or hath alreadie loſt it.</hi> That therefore wee may immitate <hi>Nature,</hi> Let the <hi>Heart</hi> nouer bee vnguarded,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173946:32"/>let religious meditations bee as veines to conuay pure thoughts from it, conſtant vnſhaken reſolutions bee the nerues, let a wall of Virtues, immure it inſtead of Ribbs, a cleare Conſcience in lieu of a defiled; ſo ſhall wee finde the motiue of al, made good, <hi>For out it come iſſues of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was <hi>Platoes</hi> aduice in his ſecond <hi>Dialogue of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, That euery Citie ſhould haue his Fountaine in the midſt of it,</hi> his reaſon, <hi>that it might be readier for vſe, either for the ordinary employments of it,</hi> or <hi>if a caſuall fire ſhould neede the helpe of it.</hi> For the ſame cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thinkes St. <hi>Chriſtome, That
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173946:32"/>bleſſed Fountaine of, bloud and water, brake forth out of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours ſide about the heart nere the middſt of him, that it might be equally neere to all, that would either drinke out of that eternall ſpring, or quench the fire with it, that either Lust or Anger had made flame. Like ſuch a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in the middſt of a beſidged Citie, ſhould the Heart of man be among his many enemies.</hi> But poyſoning of waters is the ordinary ſtratagem of warr, nor hath our great Aduerſary forgot it, He knowes that if the Fountaine of Life bee not ſpoyled, his broken Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns of death will neuer be frequented, nor can hee euer
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173946:33"/>call himſelfe his Conqueror, whoſe heart ſtands out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. It was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Italy</hi> in the Ciuill Warres: <hi>That as often as Rome was ſet on, ſhe of neceſsitie was the way of the Warre;</hi> but it fares worſe with the <hi>Heart, For as it is the firſt part of the man that liues, the laſt that dyes; ſo it is the firſt the Deuill giues aſſault vnto, and the laſt that he giues ouer; nay, were there neuer a Deuil, the Heart hath anill Spirit of 'its owne to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it.</hi> For as ſome Boroughs with vs boaſt of the Priui ledge, that they may hang &amp; draw within themſelues: ſo is the heart of man ſuch a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173946:33"/>Corporation, it may execute it ſelfe within it ſelfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Forraigne, either Iudge, or Executioner. For ſhould wee goe no further then the <hi>thought,</hi> might wee not make a ſhift to <hi>thinke</hi> our felues to hell? if we had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hands, nor eyes, nor feet, would not our hearts finde the way thither? I know we all keepe an outward ſtate with our ſinnes, as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do with their meane Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourites, we will not ſeeme to acknowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad, yet wee hugg, and play, and make wantons of them in the inward Chambers of our hearts: as if ill thoughts at
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173946:34"/>the day of Indgement would weigh no more then the ayre or the Sunne beames doe in the Scales againſt vs: but at that triall we ſhall find, that without the mercy of our God, euery looſe laſciuious <hi>thought</hi> which wee take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in, ſhall be as a ſheet of Lead to helpe to ſinke vs. <hi>Proclus</hi> tels vs a ſtory of <hi>Polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> the Tyrant, who in a viſion ſaw his <hi>Heart</hi> thrown into a boyling <hi>Caldron,</hi> where after it had bene a while tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the heat, it cryed out of the <hi>Caldron</hi> to him, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollidore, I am the cauſe to thee of all this.</hi> Nor may wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly feare, that their hearts
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173946:34"/>will really cry out ſo, who now paſſe ouer all as in a ſlumber, whoſe ill thoughts dayly vſher them to ill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe ill actions bring them in a circle backe to ill thoughts againe. For <hi>Dauid</hi> found it out, The wicked ſtill walke the round; Firſt, they act a ſinne, becauſe the thought hath pleaſed them; then they thinke that ſinn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer againe, becauſe the Act hath pleaſed them; by a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Arithmatike</hi> multiplying one ſinne into a thouſand. How then, muſt this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine be ſo pure, may not the leaſt ſtraw, nor graine of duſt be throwne into it? Cannot
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173946:35"/>the <hi>Heart</hi> ſo much as play with the Deuill? Are ill thoughts ſin; Good thoughts that are not put in execution are not rewarded, ſhall then the ill ones vnacted bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: Cannot the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Doctors of <hi>Rome</hi> excuſe, when our great God ſhall examine, may not we anſwer for our thoughts in the ſubtil La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage of their Schoole, <hi>That ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were but firſt firſt motions, therefore no ſinnes; others ſecond firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, therefore but veniall ſins.</hi> How the learned Papiſt may euade from Hell with this, I know not: but we dull <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> haue no ſuch Art, we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173946:35"/>dare not venter on it. That all our inordinate thoughts are ſinne, is our Confeſsion, for all is our ſorrow, of all is our repentance.</p>
            <p>Nor is it a wonder that thoughts ſhould be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for deeds: For, St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> ſheweth vs, <hi>That as the Deed of the band is the out ward action, ſo the Deed of the Heart is the thought. Yee haue heard,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat 5.37.28.</note> 
               <hi>it was ſaid by them of old, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, but I ſay vnto you, that whoſoeuer lookes on a woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adultery in his heart, already.</hi> For ſaith <hi>Tertullian, The will it ſelfe is imputed to it
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173946:36"/>ſelfe, nor can the beart becauſe the deede is vndone, hauing done the thought that it ſelfe could do, be excuſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Hanibal</hi> therefore was wont to ſay of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that they could not be ouer-come but in their own coun trey, So let vs vſe this Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem in fighting againſt our ſinne in the very heart, the countrey wher it breeds It was St. <hi>Bernards</hi> aduice to his Siſter, to mark wel what God ſaid of the Woman to the Serpent, <hi>Shee ſhall bruiſe his head:</hi> Hee himſelfe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, <hi>The very head of the Serpent is then truely ſaid to bee bruiſed, when ſinne is there ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173946:36"/>where it is firſt borne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.9</note> Hee is a religious <hi>Herod,</hi> that kils ſuch <hi>Inſants,</hi> nor ſhall hee want the name of <hi>happy,</hi> that daſhes theſe <hi>little ones</hi> againſt the <hi>Stone.</hi> The <hi>Ebrew</hi> hath it, <hi>againſt the Rocke.</hi> A miſery which concernes vs all, cryes St. <hi>Auguſtine, for the Rocke is Chriſt:</hi> Doth the tender <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> complaine of young growing ſinnes, of diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnruely thoughts, that break in vpon vs in the midſt of our prayers? <hi>Away with them to the Rocke;</hi> That <hi>Rocke</hi> hath ſtrength to bruiſe them: doth <hi>Luſt</hi> kindle a flame in our hearts of looſe <hi>Laſciuious regitations? Away with them
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173946:37"/>to the Rocke;</hi> that <hi>Rocke</hi> hath <hi>water to quench them.</hi> Doe we find Gods anger kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs for theſe ſinnes? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way againe to the <hi>Rocke,</hi> that <hi>Rocke</hi> hath holes to hide vs in. <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the cleft of the Rocke when he ſaw <hi>God</hi> paſsing by: but if wee once get into the cleft of this <hi>Rock,</hi> God ſhall bee alwayes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by, but neuer paſſe, ſo he is ours for euer.</p>
            <p>It can be neither time no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> labour loſt, that is ſpent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clenſing of the <hi>Fountaine,</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if any one here would th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> minute make it his work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God would bee well pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to looke downe from he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:173946:37"/>uen vpon ſuch Labourers, whom his Sonne hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bleſt, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are the cleane in heart;</hi> yet this is not enough: be thy heart as pure as Truth, as white as Snow, or Innocency, if it be a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſealed vp, onely a wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a thinking, or intending heart; nay, I may adde, if it be onely a beleeuing heart, if there be no good workes, <hi>no iſſues of Life from it,</hi> then flatter not thy ſelf that ther is any <hi>life</hi> in it. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks of ſome in his time, <hi>That God well ſatisfied, if they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged him in their hearts, howeuer in their actions they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him:</hi> Inferring from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173946:38"/>hence, that they might ſinne without forfeit of their <hi>Faith; As if</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a chaſte Adultery, without wrong to marriage;</hi> or <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly poyſon their Father, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſſe of their Pietie.</hi> But they that haue the Art to ſin, without forgoing of their <hi>Faith,</hi> may haue as ſtrange a conueyance, no doubt, to be damned without looſing of their pardon. Wee ſhould hardly ſay, a good Houſe were kept, where we neuer ſaw the Chimney ſmoake, nor Almes giuen at the gate; nor can it bee the thrift of a good ſoule, not to diſpence it hath abroad: Howſoeuer
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173946:38"/>our Clanculary concealed Saints imagine, ſhould the naturall heart contract all the heat it had within it ſelfe, neither it, nor the body could haue a being. For as in <hi>Glaſſe workes</hi> though the fire bee ſtil to be kept encloſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Furnace, yet there is ſome vent, ſome breathing for it; So when the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Heart</hi> hath entertained a veſtall fire of <hi>Faith</hi> in it; the hands cannot but bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with Charity, the Tong heated with Deuotion, and the Eyes ſparkling towards Heauen; All the out-parts muſt feele the warmth of it; for it is well obſerued, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173946:39"/>it is not ſayd, <hi>In it is life,</hi> but <hi>out of it come iſſues of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhut vp all with an obſeruation of St. <hi>Cyrils, The Heart of man is like the Rodde of</hi> Moſes, <hi>as long as he held it in his hand, it remained a Roll, but when hee threw it to the ground, it turned to bee a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> nay, <hi>a Dragon, the Prince of Serpents,</hi> as <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew ſaith. So the Heart of man as long as there is faſt hold of it, as long as man is the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor, God the Guardian, it continues ſtill a Heart, but if our boyſterous vnruly ſinnes once throwe it to the earth, it changeth inſtantly, to be a Serpent. So let mee beſeech
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173946:39"/>as many as heare me to day, whoſe Conſciences this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute tells them, that their <hi>Hearts</hi> are turned into <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> and are now crawling on the earth, to ſtretch forth a hand of ſorrow, a hand of true repentance, to take them vp againe, in what ſhape ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they appeare. For he that was exalted on the Croſſe, as the Serpent in the wildernes, ſhall turne thoſe Serpents into Hearts againe, their gall and poyſon into Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, their ſting of Death, into <hi>Iſſues</hi> of immortall <hi>life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lay vp therefore theſe Memorialls yee that loue your <hi>Hearts,</hi> Lay them vp
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173946:40"/>yee that doe not, that you may loue them. Remember the <hi>Heart</hi> is a <hi>Iewell</hi> of Gods owne cutting, the ſubſtance and faſhion of it is heauenly. Remember it is the <hi>Glaſſe</hi> that God delights to looke in, why ſhould you breake it and ſcatter it? It is his <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſent from Himſelfe to Himſelfe, why ſhould you either blot, or falſifie; or not deliuer it where it is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? It is his <hi>Coyne,</hi> his <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> why ſhould you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualue it? It is his <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> his <hi>Temple,</hi> and his <hi>Altar,</hi> why ſhould you prophane it? But if the Deuill hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne ſo powerfull as to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173946:40"/>ſtrike out the memory of all this: Yet remember it is that <hi>Iewell,</hi> which <hi>Man</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forfeited, the <hi>Sonne of God</hi> was faine to dye for to redeeme it. So that hee that dares looſe his <hi>Heart</hi> againe, dares crucifie his <hi>God</hi> againe. Remember next, the pure Eyes of the <hi>Angels,</hi> that like the eyes of a wel-drawne <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> are faſtned on you which way ſoeuer you turn. Remember the neuer-ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>God</hi> that is all Eye to bee your Guardian, vntill that your wilfull ſinnes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe him from you with all his Angels. Remember laſt of all, that this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:173946:41"/>watch is not ſet about dead Treaſure. That as the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Orbes haue a motion of their owne, though moo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued perpetually by the <hi>Firſt Eternall Moouer:</hi> So thought the Powers of Heauen bee ſet to Guard you, yet this excuſeth not the Guard you are to ſet vpon your felues; for if a man keepe not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, God doth not keepe him. Keepe therefore your <hi>Hearts</hi> through all the wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Night; from the twilight, to the crowing of the Cock; from the crowing of the Cocke to the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day; from the Mantle to the Winding-ſheet;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173946:41"/>ſheete; from the Cradle, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Graue. Let neither ill <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houghts</hi> pollute the <hi>Spring,</hi> nor <hi>foule deeds</hi> the <hi>Riuer;</hi> ſo ſhall there from thence <hi>come Iſſues of life,</hi> not onely the life of nature, which the worſt men haue, nor onely the life of <hi>Grace,</hi> which the <hi>Good</hi> haue here, but the life of <hi>Glory,</hi> which the <hi>Saints</hi> haue in the world to come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
